All right welcome back we're live here
...three build twenty fifteen so far it's been pretty cool and awesome
...I'm here with caring gala tell us what do you do for microsoft I run the
windows developer platform teamwhen the program management team there some responsible for
the api...tools and make sure that developers have what they need to build great apps
for windows that's awesome so look the thing about channel...makes the best...your
question so please have the maybe want to see your questions let me start with one of my
own there is a new universal windows platform what does that mean
and how do you distinguish that from universal windows apps the universe windows
platform is what is available across all of the windows ten device family
...lots of different family devices but the platform is available across all of them are
universal windows app is an...that's written that runs on top of that platform now you may have
done specialization to make that app...work a one device versus the other
is a might need some...your harbor capabilities on a device
...universal windows app because it runs on that universe someone this platform also in
...universal windows platform what sort of...family of products
can-we argue...the...get the full list of that I now I cause I looked it up and
...yesterday so many there's this like we...of
...so what are some of the work-site wants to start...maybe some...so obviously, you know,
about hollow...a...of as a great collaborative device can make sense
...meeting rooms and showrooms,
yeah, we have xbox obviously great well-known part of the family
give you desktop which includes your laptop your to...pc's?
Then you have phones fab let's tablets...and things like that
it's a pretty and wider range...will data screen which obviously is io...
ultimately be...the most prolific of them all right so I mean this is a pretty
wide range of options how do we help developers build universal
windows app such that they don't have to righted new thing for everyone of those options
...was a lot of writing I tried to say yesterday...kind of repeatable the flow which is,
you know, when you building the application you can share the code but what you're going to
use on each device maybe for different purpose what I do of my follow might be different what I want to do and
...obviously a...that tv or the service have
one kind of collaborating rise as you're building that you want to think about what is the best device
...for this part of my tacit...part of my workflow
...then tuning the experience for...want...run that...other devices could
...I have a larger screens I want to get it done on my phone or I
...my...too lazy to go walk over to my pc right so you want to
make it functional doer to for devices that can really make it...more productive experience
...so there was a promise that hey if you bright a universal windows app it'll just
worked everywhere but do we necessarily want to do with that way so the...
are available so you can write to those api is it's also not the does not
...half be available everywhere there are api that are only available
in certain devices...if certain hardware is plugged in the not everything has a...right
...tv typically doesn't have a pen so try use a penny api need japanese take into account
...is no pen...gave controller or use
mouse keyboard or what do I do my app that can fall back in some cases, you know,
like for camera you have a fallback my tv doesn't have a calmer in most cases,
you know, so, I'm not going to go do that, you know, so, you kind of...the app
...purpose but the api the platforms consistent...like if the
relearn different things we have a new thing called api contracts so you can say hey is this
api available on platform if it is that I can light up that code if not then
...some fallback behavior really that's like a really cool way of doing it because the problem is
if you're building for this device it has its own thing you...for this...as on...you literally have to
spend up to teams just for those...devices both consistent api as you can do a lot of
...work right you...the shared portion of it all the common code we written
...experts for the specialization they can write that specialization
...have questions coming in one will more information on developing universal windows apps
on xbox be available so
...platform is the same across all of devices so how you
build the application...tools and all that is all available
...what I think you might be ask is when can I have either emulator
and xbox or some way to test it and see the experience there now we're not
...announcing yet but soon we'll be discussing how you can get...in this type of thing
senescence if you're building if you if you want to target eventually xbox just build a windows ten
...and you're going to be well on your way to
...cool all right another question if I were to develop and app for windows
tag what I have to implement support for keyboard mouse and heights so,
you know,
you're not required to implements anything I mean it's really about where
your targeting so-if you...ship of for app just for phones it only made sense...
phones you really want to about...kiwi even those,... attached to it and you go build that
unit optimize user experience...by default most of our controls will
work with mouse and keyboard if they were attached but that's not required to do the work we definitely
...want to be the wow you have a lot of devices so the first step in I gotta go make sure my
ux works role that...say hey pick a device come in their
...great for that device that form factor that input model then tested on the other
ones and incremental work as you find valuable them across the entire family
...most cases it will just work and he's a little bit tuning so this brings up
a larger philosophical question should we shouldn't really be building the same
map across all the form factors because each form factor has specific beings that
...let it be good at something else and
that's absolutely case we talk about the one binary case and...I think continuum
is really while...what one binary is a I mean these...running and I want to be a
tableau desktop mode on the photo...being phone mode on desktop mode that's
...one binary really is an advantage on the other hand if you want to build a great app
for one device specially for...dedicated
...coyote...that it may really only work on
one io to device with a certain set of sensors and that's what will work well for that
...totally able equal different binary for each platform for one
...windows ten you can literally build whatever device you want when you're speaking
coyote to do whatever you walk absolutely so that's cool all right and all you skills that you've learned
...can all be...it can any...thirty-two application
windows ten call universal windows platform api or does it need to be submitted
...the windows store for so the first...what to make sure that when you use...
packaging deployments when you basically take a wintry to application and put into it
app x package that you can use that across-the-board you can silo install that or
get to the store...from the store so the ability to build a package
at the...that'll be inside this
...outside the store it's just a new deployment model we've had for wintry to apps the
leverage say
...have universal the second thing is for the api some many of the api
...will work without having identity but there are many api is like be able
to get notifications
I pushed education where we need to have an identity in order to have a identity you need
to registered with the store and that you will need to build communicate register with
the store have an identity then we know which app to pushed...to
...doing it for no reason like yet to be in-store no we need identity to push
...you know, to push like notification got to instead of api so
in essence if you want to have some of the other benefits to store brings like identity push notifications
should but if you don't care about that you're drawing you're making a drawing app that you don't care who's white
...you...good and it's just a better...install technology where we can
install, install and keep it updated...so that's really just a net benefit of the better
installation so what do these dot net compile apps look like when you
for...app x what is how does that process work so I would
...I said...affects the of the app acts as a replacement for
...so emphasized occur way many people deploy applications
now sport fx you now take your app put into it app
acts and you can deploy doing that there's some constraints there that emphasize didn't have
...deploy kernel mode driver...services
those if you those things we're not going to support coming from the store because we just don't like
the lead to a good customer experience court and they can be abused
...what's good all right let's go to john art
...windows platform dot net apps compiled to any cpu or is
there binary for each architecture compiled separately we actually compile
...architecture separately that's awesome okay peter...why build
a uw universal windows app now that ios android code will run on windows
...so as a great question I a we...that...numerous times
so you should look at the ios...code as a starting point
...the bridge analogy because that's when you start we really want the destination is
...be building a universal windows application may reason is
...get better ui is adaptive ui works continuum...works
...core...it works at all in...all of
these cool features the real goal of allow you to leverage echoed is
...we don't want you have to rewrite code that works that has no value to rewrites,
yeah,...like if...just...and I didn't needed there's no benefit to rewriting it why should
I...goal there is to make sure that you can use that
...reuse it into your application much like middleware and this...tennessee people going
towards model where they have a shared code base at the...across may different platforms
and then they build specialization for any...ui for each device...on
the look best on that device...if you want to build a great universe windows app
...that code and then you'll adam and spend all your time on being better
...windows I...you spend your time porting code that's good that actually...no value on windows
itself so it if you just want to move it over as a starting point but then
...take over some of the other features that windows tag gives you so maybe it's time to
start for bridging away all right that's we try to show little bit of in
...is a here the...running but look I get xbox live integration I get core
...integration I get inky idea...is that we can all these different great
features and that's we should spend your time as developers is making the app great got it so
...the api contract mean I don't need conditional compilation the different devices even if I
use device specific stuff yes that is the goal that you will not need to have
if depths to do the compilation stead the app
...adapt and dynamically light up different port part functionality based on whether that
harbors available that feature...is available in my head I mean this makes a little bit more sense because then you can write
for ahold your own way of saying which device...using this is what I
want to light up this is what I don't want to light up ok next can universal apps communicate with
wc have services if so are all the...supported if not what
technologies recommended for communicating with the windows service so I don't know enough
...you...sub-part on that question...detailed that much of...think
it will not work but I have not validated that's right that's ok so if you want to communicate,
you know, to your as...back-end services what's the best way to do that using windows up I think
...a set of services...services that we all into...case additional just worked
out okay cool so let's go let's move on...a couple more question but I have another some questions
that I want to ask you if it looks like during this sort of build conference we've been talking
about some really cool controls that you're adding to the universal windows platform you
...about what those are so first of all there's some that we didn't have everywhere and I think
...I think pivots a great control works well now...on phone now we have
...desktop is a great control for...different panels and...tab control but it's
a it's a nice interactive control worth...toward and, types and game controller got
we obviously of introduce split you control which is very popular you seeing a lot of our applications
...you know, those misstated you yone some of the more rich ones like the in canvas that
right just enable absolutely phenomenal capabilities all wrapped up in a
...to get editing selection all this stuff rich drawing
...including handling pain, you know,
touch all that stuff is a great control of course the map control that I
showed which is just phenomenal having ariel having offline two-d capabilities
...if you just want to work your application it's
...all right so the one I saw that to be struck me was the
gain control there were some really cool stuff that you could really do up
like demo you did was you circled...started moving things around and the code
wasn't too complicated tell us what about the api...it seems really well-thought-out,
yeah, so, we did a lot of work in...inc to layer the api we have direct
think is really the platform and now we built on top of that in canvas and...
open to control it knows about selection in those about being able to draw those that editing
this...edit those conses the built into the control very naturally
easily so yet...back-end and you can control that experience exactly
...want it also does great palm rejection in those how to use touch versus
...not all those all nuggets in it the may great
it's actually the same control being used by microsoft edge...right almost to the code name
...and, it's all built in...as well that's awesome so it's not
...just making things...making things and using them in our products and
...our customers...to all right so I've got some questions but looks like
...scrolls so let's scroll down a little bit so I can so I
...I want to get some questions let me ask about the map control what are some of the
...features that you think the mapinfo exposes to universal windows platform
developed so it's obviously all the user having great naturally
you interactions with it all built-in first of all...don't have to do anything
...be on the data bind all of these...are layer bottle sets of
...and filter the naturally...click on...can navigate into the
...all this works great I mean it's a rich control that's awesome I think the map
is pry one of the best visualizations because it gives you that extra dimension of information that's
really contextual all right so...getting the questions here scroll I...ask you about io
...when I bought my raspberry
ply too because I was the first I wanted one of those things
...windows really run on that and what can you do with it what kind of api
...exposing to work with io...
Yeah, so, it is windows in lilies running the same version of windows.
Exactly very the same version of windows as you so I wrote the same applications
so you can take those apps and write them run them it also has the
ability to hook into a several different types of buses they can plug-in...peripherals
and now you can actually just a page...to that code in the universe...and even if those
sensor attached with desktop what...hardware those api work pilgrims
...ot...a devices now that have those buses on them now
...and universal just enumerate through the buses are obviously
there's some api contract that you have we've had several namespaces for those gets obviously cup,
you know, how to identify this device how to communicate to it but all that
...control they used to be built into a...now built into...itself all that's
...be so nice because nobody likes writing device drivers I'm just saying we don't either
I know that better...the ability for everyone to side load when
...if you're she likes to...be similar strict restrictions
...apps so on the desktop you'll
build a silo them just like you do any wintry to application so have a
...policy for any application that you have out there so the
other side load we will have restrictions or other devices...be device dependence got it sort of
...continue you have to be developer unlocked which...made a lot easier of what
...limited to twenty-year is a certain
reasonable number that's all you can...on the phone like of...desktop...unlimited number, you know,
I like making software I just don't like the idea of having to worry about selling
...where do I put it so I like the idea of having store but I mean whatever you want
to you can do it all right can you talk a bit about how side loading works
for development for production so you said styling works on the desktop...just
you build your own of a...before you basically once you create epics package
...api says and package...as...it is simple as
...you install it...if we have a handle yet
...can double-click on them or not,... that simple...libra it should be a...double-click
...site launches installer double-click on app exited installs ego the, you know,
program list you install it was kind of anti climactic...like that ok now that
when thirty-two can be published in the windows store will look current mandatory
full windows size splash...present windows store apps also be mandatory with...to store?
I hope not you have got...policies
...event idea at my sense is that we just want people to use
their old with thirty-two applications on windows...yeah, they gassed all-new api
...stormy actually a better say this is I want my...have all the apps everybody wants I like they're
a whole lot of wintry to dot net applications that people want to go to store yet to make to
store the onestop place they go get everything that they're interested in getting and that's good for
...are not the now we're stuff...today,...that's...stuff we don't want all right so there are
...more questions will ported android ios abs run on the
whole universal windows platform pc phone service of poland's io
...sothis site differences there for ios
...code the code me jeff to see that code is possible to wrong because when we
act compile it is directly compile by visual studio and note in the
apple actually run across all those devices now be clear I'll know that you have a great experience
...with the user interface...comes them...unit was not...designed our goal
is to...label you in the future...be able to take advantage of universally
...example and web to...to build new interface on top of that to do that we're
workingto unlocked that functionality but, you can bring it will give you use experience
...function for android apps are running right now they will actually only run on
mobile got it but the reality is mobile...both these anybody's
...privacy android is a mobile experience they built...I would you
...a reasonable experience from the if you want something better...to use more of the universal platform
...those things to make it better and...got it brand
...what are the core differences between windows eight when rt based apps and windows
ten universal...to feels like there's a lot that's...it's just an evolution ado we actually
last year introduced of our universe laps and I usually call that the universal windows
eight...universal windows ten platform so it's just
a version ever-changing you look at example you have javascript support,
support cplus-plus csharp vb, you know, all the same stuff we support before we
have deprecated anything all we've done is add more api
...add more functionality that big change that can require some work by developers...did
build universal windows eight apps is the control set the change because we had
emerging make sure that you that app...cross...pc and be a single binary
right controls...change so when you move over you might have to change the why the layouts
change slightly so that's where the bulk of the work will go,
you know,...degree deprecated that many api...it's mostly additive
...set changed and that will
...run if you don't change the apple run exactly as they did...what do
upgrade the project from a project to attend project for visual studio in visual
studio...have to deal with some of the...that...us all right another question what do I need
to develop and xbox box apps not the game xbox app nottingham
...there so it's visual studio basically you just building a universal windows
app will be the same exact...just be able to go there and say, you know,
connect to the xbox you...xbox once you get to developer
...got all right another question if I want to develop a cross-platform dot
net for library do I still need to...a pc a library or
will didn't dot net core eventually be truly cross-platform without the need for api
...setting so that's a very technical bunch yes and I are actually know
exactly details to that one so I'm going to I'm not going to try to answer that
what it seems like you pry well but I'm not positive exactly what's in core that's not
in the pcs upsetting if you build
...new universal windows app that
you're guaranteed that is going to be able to work across all the platforms that is...case?
So, is this question?
For dot net core, yeah,
this is dot...core and I'm not sure the answers as we're not sure ok so
...me this is a new...endeavour...a little bit because people might be...
what does that mean if you do file new windows ten windows ten app that will just work across yeah,
that's...
to build universal application the set of net that's in universe application model will
...across everything we have a very large set of the api...we've added...talk
that specifically but we have added to the universe api set in large number of things that came
from dot net large number of x additional wintry to api gobi that's going to move from
wintry to our dot net you...build universal...reuse it much your code the same flask you
...for ios android web is reuse as much of the code that existed that we could
just bring that into the universal windows platform...here's a really good question from scott I'm about
to release windows eight-point one phone eight-point one app to three...I wait and
convert to universal windows app well.
There are no universal there are no devices today out there other than
...by insiders that would run that universal windows at so I would say I
would release your current prior to all your customers and then once we
...the platform then you could upgrade to universe
...at...you might also be able to experimental...and use when
...twenty fifteen rc and say hey let me up and see what happens so you could do that
we would not how he said wait about releasing...release now
...early and often actually be more clear you should go release that try
to upgrade give us feedback on how well it works...what...that intel's...doesn't work or not it's really
about you release the products by tell us we need to go do tells you
...the problems things that...fix now before release to make that process
...upgrading...your app hoosier got it okay so I'm going to
...question because this is something that I've I'm not a very good design so what are some things example
affords me that will help me like some of the controls that will help may be able to build
something that truly works across device.
So, we've spent insane amount of time with our design team getting use
...user feedback with our controls team
...should controls...build work nicely and scale across all the different
form factors and the different equipment modalities in tour-de-force control
...we feel very good about now what I really...say think is the base
...you build your button disclosure size those are the most important
right you in many times you move between different
apple different device for factors the top-level navigation
...you interact with that I think you tend to more what all the base control...work
guys so we did the...the base controls function actually...just a cycle that top-level
...navigated laid out see that all the examples I did...move things around a little bit things top
...bible top of each other with the relative panel adaptive state triggers you can do those
lightweight layout changes in all the controls...just work soil change the
...panel and almost everything else will just is there is...like,
for example, if I building I if I if I'm
...target tablet and the phone because that's what my I want my app to do is
their way example to say.
My other phone or a...you have to make a sample page
each of the windows that you're going to be in the bits today I don't know that's there is a way figured
...complex within a simplified streamlining we do find that...phone versa tablet
...one handed mode got what have...headed...versus, you know,
tablet definitely have to ended...you can you
...site so...slightly different...between the two and yes you'll be able to say hey which data by
...will find adaptive trigger...just user...home about
adapted triggers what are those so adaptive triggers of fired when you basically set
up of several set of states windows states fire you can change attributes on
...the layouts...any code to design it can go in there and say, you know, okay,
what I'm smaller I want to...to the sides and...top of each other and portrait
mode typically...other...in vertical I want to be able to...mode
want them side-by-side of in the with...so those simple things or you do a set
of some triggers you tell it what attributes...changed and
...to change for you got...a question to check if a device
depending api is present you currently parser query with a little...api class?
That this is like a long statement that seems like a really good feature requests when you
ask mass targets...the I'll ask...we're going to go to
...to extend the new name of expert, yeah, I mean for...that's a little a so
...question...good feature requests will take into account
see so the question is how do you check for device dependence right now we do
is...api contract they actually did a couple different ways
we recommend is checklist api contract because...challenge if you ask
for specific device that device may ad that functionality later
on and then your check is incorrect right so it's check the weather not the api is
...if those api contract is...call the eight guys if not, you know,
do some alternate behavior we will...the ability to query
...which device among...because sometimes the actual device
mattersshe would be different business decisions based on the device, you know, it feels like more important
it's what's your screen size and what you have available and that really should define
your it's it doesn't some cases but, for example,
there's...status bar on the phone there is no status bar on
any the other devices got it but you...talk to that status
...do say well hey if the status bar contract is there then I want to tell the status
...to show different,
different different...are running out of time where can people go to find out more
and get started these deadwindows dot com and just go there and
learn what's the most exciting thing?
You think in that sort of the new set of things were rolling out what
...you most excited about wow, that's negative...somebody else will tell me
...impact...maybe like two or seven or twelve.
I think its most powerful for developers...because we have this breath of hardware I think without
adaptive ui if you challenging I do think all this stuff work we've done example with
a lot of performance work I'd say it's most...delve output to be a target this
heartless ecosystem is breadth of hardware that we've got so it's not a complex
...a very straightforward in simple problem...thanks so much for spending some
time with us thanks for watching and we'll see you after the break take care thanks.